Finding Aid for Henry Bourne Joy Papers 1883-1937
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Bourne Joy Papers 1883-1937
Joy, Henry Bourne, 1864-1936.
2 oversize volumes
2 oversize folders
19 linear feet
851730 Aa 2 AC Ac UAm
Detroit financier and industrialist, president of Packard Motor Car Company, leader of the "Good Roads Movement" and president of the Lincoln Highway Association, active in the Republican Party and business associations. Papers include correspondence, scrapbooks and photographs relating to automobile business, cross country auto travels and Joy's political interests.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 1946 by Mrs. Henry Bourne Joy (donor no. 2204 ).
The collection is open for research.
Henry Bourne Joy was a Detroit financier and industrialist. Born November 23, 1864 to railroad magnate James Frederick Joy, Henry B. Joy early on appreciated the importance of gasoline engines, first for marine use and then for automobiles. He was an investor in the Packard Motor Car Company. He was general manager of the company from 1903 to 1909 and president from 1909 to 1916. For the next two years, Joy was board chairman serving until 1918 when he retired from the company. Realizing the importance of roads to his company, Joy was an important advocate of the good roads movement, serving for a time as president of the Lincoln Highway Association. Prior to America's entry into World War I, Joy, concerned about the nation's preparedness for war, successfully urged the Packard Company to become a manufacture of airplanes for military use.
Joy was a man of many other interests and activities. Because of his yachting interests and service aboard the U.S.S. Yosemite during the Spanish-American War, Joy was a keen observer of the naval affairs of the nation. At one time he served as vice president of the Navy League of the United States. Additionally he was a member of the Federal Reserve Bank for the Chicago district and active in Republican party politics and other conservative causes and organizations. Among his other deeply held views was an abhorrence of the Prohibition Amendment, Roosevelt's New Deal, and the intrusion of the church in public affairs.
Joy died November 6, 1936.
The collection has been divided into the following series:
Biographical Materials
Correspondence
Photographs/Photograph Albums
Scrapbooks
Published Materials
Miscellaneous
The Henry B. Joy papers consist of correspondence concerning his business activities in Detroit, Michigan, his support of the Lincoln Highway Association, his campaign against the Eighteenth Amendment (Prohibition), and their interest in the Federal Council of Churches; also business letter books, 1888-1892, and 1902-1903; photograph album, 1915, concerning automobile trip from Detroit to San Francisco; scrapbooks, 1883-1937, containing newspaper clippings and articles relating to the development of the automobile industry, national economic affairs and Republican politics; and collection of printed pamphlets and newsletters, 1927-1936, of conservative individuals and organizations, including the American Coalition, American Liberty League, the Vigilant Intelligence Federation, the Daughters of the American Revolution, Elizabeth Dilling, Robert E. Edmonson, the Industrial Defense Association, the National Civic Federation, and the Union League of Michigan. The collection also includes photograph albums of cross-country automobile trips and of racing cars; also portraits of Joy.
Subjects:
American Coalition.; American Liberty League.; American Vigilant Intelligence Federation.; Association Against the Prohibition Amendment.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--Detroit.; Banks and banking--United States.; Business records.; Conservatism.; Daughters of the American Revolution. National Defense Committee.; Detroit (Mich.); Detroit Athletic Club.; Stokes, Elizabeth Dilling, 1894-1966.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931.; Edmonson, Robert Edward.; Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America.; The Fundamentalist.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Industrial Defense Association.; Joy, Henry Bourne, 1864-1936.; Joy, James Frederick, 1810-1896.; Lincoln Highway Association.; Michigan Naval Brigade.; Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Michigan--Politics and government--1917-1921.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; National Civic Federation.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.; Packard Motor Car Company.; Presidents--United States--Election--1916.; Prohibition--United States.; Radio broadcasting--United States.; Republican Party (Mich.); Roads--United States.; Silver question.; Tariff--United States.; Automobile travel--United States.; Union League of Michigan.; United States. Federal Reserve Board.; United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.; Vanderbilt Cup Races.; World War, 1914-1918.; Spanish-American War, 1898.
Contributors:
Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Hunter, Edward, 1902-1978.; Jung, Harry A.; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987.; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1939.; Peabody, Frederick William, 1862-1938; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Slayton, William H.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.
Visual Materials - Subjects:
Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Hunter, Edward, 1902-1978.; Jung, Harry A.; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987.; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1939.; Peabody, Frederick William, 1862-1938; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Slayton, William H.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical Materials
  Biographical Materials is a small series consisting of autobiographical sketches written by Joy on different phases in his life.
  - Autobiographical sketches (Box 1)
    (Boyhood of Henry B. Joy; With James Joy in England, July 1884; Controversy with Henry Ward Beecher; Development of Aviation Interest in Detroit)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, except for a scattering of letters, dates primarily from the period following Joy's retirement from the Packard Motor Car Company in 1918. The letters concern Joy's various political and public interests: his opposition to the 18th Amendment (Prohibition), his interests in the nation's naval readiness, his support of measures to improve America's roads, and his opposition to some of the activities of the Federal Council of Churches. Joy corresponded widely with various public figures. His correspondents include James J. Couzens, Elizabeth Dilling; Warren G. Harding; Charles E. Hughes; Edward Hunter; Harry A. Jung; Alfred M. Landon; Andrew W. Mellon; Truman H. Newberry; Franklin D. Roosevelt; Theodore Roosevelt; Elihu Root; William H. Slayton and William H. Taft. In addition to the files of correspondence, the collection includes two volumes of letterpress books of Joy's business activities. The volumes are dated 1888-1892 and 1902-1903.
  - 1897 1908-May 10, 1928 (Box 1)
  - May 11, 1928-January 16, 1930 (Box 2)
  - January 16, 1930-November 6, 1930 (Box 3)
  - November 7, 1930-March 14, 1932 (Box 4)
  - March 15, 1932-May 1933 (Box 5)
  - January 1932-May 18, 1932 (Box 6)
  - May 19, 1936-October 18, 1936 (Box 7)
  - October 19, 1936-October 1937 (Box 8)
  - Business letterpress volumes of correspondence
    - 1888-1892 (Box 8)
    - 1902-1903 (Box 8)
- Photographs / Photograph Albums
  The Photographs/Photograph Albums series documents early trips made by Joy on the Lincoln Highways. One was a trip from Detroit to San Francisco in 1915; another is an undated tour "from coast to coast" in a Packard Motor Car. Other albums are of the Vanderbilt Cup Automobile Racers (1906) and a trip in a Packard "Six." See also Ac and UAm
  - Photographs, miscellaneous, 1 envelopes (Box 9)
    (includes portraits and photographs of Joy in or along side different automobiles)
  - Photograph album of A Family Tour from Coast to Coast in a Packard Motor Car undated (Box 9)
  - Photograph album of Vanderbilt Cup Automobile Racers 1906 (Box 9)
  - Photograph album of test trip in Packard "Six"; volume entitled "Three Men in a 'Six'" (Box 9)
  - Photograph album of Packard and Liberty-12 airplane engines, including description by Alvan Macauley and letter of Henry B. Joy 1918 (Box 9)
  - Photograph album of automobile trip to New Mexico [outsize] March 1914 (Volume 1)
  - Photograph album of trip from Detroit to San Francisco on Lincoln Highway May-June 1915, [outsize] (Volume 2)
- Scrapbooks
  The greatest part of the collection consists of Scrapbooks, dated from 1883 to 1936, and consisting of clippings, memorabilia, and scattered correspondence detailing Joy's various interests and activities. Subjects include the Lincoln Highway, the development of the Packard Motor Car Company, the Michigan Naval Reserve, national tariff policy, the prohibition amendment, and state and national politics.
  - Vol. I, Scrapbook 1890-1898 (Box 10)
    (subjects include Detroit Athletic Club, Michigan State Naval Brigade (1st Division), Free Silver question, Taxation of railroads)
  - Vol. II, Scrapbook 1896-1899 (Box 10)
    (miscellaneous, J. F. Joy, H. B. Joy)
  - Vol. III, Scrapbook concerning the Michigan Naval Reserves 1898 (Box 10)
  - Vol. IV, Scrapbook concerning the Michigan Naval Reserves 1898-1899 (Box 10)
  - Vol. V, Scrapbook concerning the Michigan Naval Reserves 1900-1928 (Box 10)
  - Vol. VI, Scrapbook 1883-1913 (Box 11)
    (subjects include personal miscellanea, automobile development, Truman H. Newberry, Packard Motor Car Company)
  - Vol. VII, Scrapbook 1908-1910 (Box 11)
    (subjects include tariff question, employers liability law)
  - Vol. VIII, Scrapbook concerning automobiles and the tariff question 1912 (Box 11)
  - Vol. IX, Scrapbook concerning automobiles and the tariff question 1913-1915 (Box 11)
  - Vol. X, Scrapbook concerning the Packard Motor Car Co. and national business developments 1913-1914 (Box 11)
  - Vol. XI, Scrapbook 1913-1916 (Box 12)
    (subjects include child labor, advertising ethics, newspaper boycott)
  - Vol. XII, Scrapbook concerning price cutting 1913-1916 (Box 12)
  - Vol. XIII, Scrapbook 1913-1916 (Box 12)
    (subjects include Lincoln Highway, war preparedness)
    [microfilm copy available]
  - Vol. XIV, Scrapbook concerning interstate and foreign commerce 1914 (Box 12)
  - Vol. XV, Scrapbook 1913-1915 (Box 13)
    (subjects include national politics Federal Reserve Board, Good Roads Movement, gasoline substitute)
  - Vol. XVI, Scrapbook concerning Federal Reserve Board, 1915 (Box 13)
  - Vol. XVII, Scrapbook concerning Lincoln Highway (vol. 1) 1915-1916 (Box 13)
  - Vol. XVIII, Scrapbook concerning Lincoln Highway (vol. 2) 1915-1916 (Box 13)
  - Vol. XIX, Scrapbook 1915-1930 (Box 14)
    (subjects include World War I, social affairs)
  - Vol. XX, Scrapbook concerning the Presidential election campaign of Charles Evans Hughes 1916 (Box 14)
  - Vol XXI, Scrapbook 1916-1926 (Box 14)
    (subjects include War with Pancho Villa, Roosevelt Republican League of Michigan, Packard Motor Car Co., Lincoln Highway, aviation developments)
  - Vol XXII, Scrapbook 1921-1930 (Box 14)
    (subjects include social affairs Grosse Pointe, Mich., Radio developments, Packard Motor Car Co., Thomas A. Edison, Prohibition, Federal Council of Churches)
  - Vol. XXIII, Scrapbook concerning prohibition 1925-1931 (Box 15)
  - Vol. XXIV, Scrapbook concerning war debts question 1927-1932 (Box 15)
  - Vol. XXV, Scrapbook 1931-1933 (Box 15)
    (subjects include Abraham Lincoln research, Navy League of the United States, Republican politics)
  - Vol. XXVI, Scrapbook 1931-1934 (Box 16)
    (subjects include Detroit banks, Federal Council of Churches, income tax, economic conditions)
  - Vol. XXVII, Scrapbook 1933-1936 (Box 16)
    (subjects include banking crisis, New Deal, American Liberty League, economic conditions)
  - Vol. XXVIII, Scrapbook 1936-1937 (Box 16)
    (subjects include Federal Council of Churches)
  - Vol XXIX, Scrapbook concerning Helen Joy Lee, 1918-1928 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 3 folders (Box 16)
- Printed pamphlets, newsletters and reports 1927-1936
  Joy was a member and supporter of numerous politically and socially conservative organizations, and his collection includes the published pamphlets, newsletters, and reports distributed by these groups. The series, called Published Materials, includes anti-prohibition, anti-New Deal literature, as well as publications of the American Liberty League, Elizabeth Dilling, and Robert E. Edmonson. The Miscellaneous series includes guide books to countries in which Joy traveled. There is also a copy of the testimony given by Joy in 1923 before Secretary of Agriculture Henry C. Wallace concerning Lincoln Highway in Utah and Nevada.
  - American in Danger (Charles B. Hudson) (Box 17)
  - American Coalition (Box 17)
  - American Liberty League (Box 17)
  - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Box 17)
  - D.A.R. National Defense Committee (Box 17)
  - Dilling, Elizabeth (Box 17)
  - Edmondson, Robert Edward (Box 17)
  - Federal Council of Churches (Box 17)
  - The Fundamentalist (Box 17)
  - Industrial Control Reports (Box 17)
  - Industrial Defense Association (Box 17)
  - Law Suit (University of Detroit) (Box 17)
  - Mailing Lists (Box 17)
  - National Civic Federation (Box 17)
  - National defense (miscellaneous) (Box 18)
  - New Deal (opposition forces) (Box 18)
  - Prohibition (Box 18)
  - "Red Menace" (Miscellaneous) (Box 18)
  - Union League of Michigan (Box 18)
  - War debt question (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Better America Federation, R.O.T.C. association, Madame Cantacuzene) (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous writings and newspaper clippings (Box 18)
  - Pamphlets concerning anti-prohibition campaign, anti-New Deal, and American Liberty League (Box 18)
  - Pamphlets concerning D.A.R. National Defense Committee, Robert E. Edmondson, Elizabeth Dilling (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous
  - Guide books to England and other countries traveled (Box 19)
  - Testimony before Secretary of Agriculture Henry C. Wallace concerning Lincoln Highway in Utah and Nevada, 1923 (Box 19)
  - Proclamation of the Rout of the Lincoln Highway, 1913 (Box 19)
    (oversize item in Ac folder)